this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Robert bloomin editor
of software engineering radio if you're
hearing this that means you're a
listener of the show but have you ever
thought about being a host it's a great
way to talk to some of the most
interesting people in the industry and
get 30 to 40 thousand people to hear
your thoughts
contact us team @ SC - radio net for
more information your code is powerful
and so are you and when you consider the
reach of your code it's clear that to
deliver quality code you must also
deliver secure code where can you start
a first step is educating yourself on
basic secure coding principles and
beginning to put these principles into
practice every day very codes secure
coding toolkit is your go-to resource
for all your secure coding needs the
benefits of our tool kit include
learning best practices for secure
coding understanding how to secure your
DevOps environments learning to combat
the most common software vulnerabilities
stay secure and download this valuable
asset today
ww-where code comm / SC radio this is
Nate black for software engineering
radio my guest today is Joel Spolsky
Joel is CEO and co-founder of stack
overflow prior to stack overflow he was
co-founder of fog Creek software which
spun off Trello which is now part of
Atlassian and is now producing glitch
Joel welcome to software engineering
radio thanks and thank you for having me
on it's nice to be here it's a pleasure
to have you here your bio on your blog
Joel on software comm says very modestly
that you're a software developer living
in New York City okay technically true
yeah technically true but I think
probably everyone listening to this show
has used Stack Overflow and probably a
lot of them have used the other products
that you've produced i hope though i
just want to give our listeners a sense
of scale of what Stack Overflow is like
today just to put things in perspective
sure it's big there's a few different
ways we look at it one one thing that
surprises people is that it's a top 50
website globally I think and it kind of
depends on whose traffic metrics you're
looking at but we've been at top 50
website for a long time and we get more
unique visitors in apple.com which sort
of surprises people part of it really is
you can't talk to a developer that
doesn't use Stack Overflow regularly so
it's kind of a required part to a
required tool for doing software
development and that's pretty amazing
because I don't know how many other
required tools there are you know
everybody has some kind of version
control but I think there maybe there's
some popular ones like it but there's
some variety there now you need two
compiler but everything's got a
different compiler but you kind of can't
live without Stack Overflow yeah that's
true and I'd like to talk more later in
the show about effective ways of using
Stack Overflow since it is required
skill nowadays but before that and I
want to get to know a little bit more
about your story and the story of Stack
Overflow sure can you tell me a little
bit about how that came about
yeah sort of strange most people when
they tell the story of their company
don't usually have to introduce it in
terms of another company and so we kind
of started as a reaction to experts
exchange which at this point thankfully
not a lot of developers even remember
but if you were a developer and you were
working in the Europe before experts
exchange and you had a problem
programming and you typed it into Yahoo
or Alta Vista or even Google at some
point you often ended up an experts
exchange which was one of the early
programming forums I wouldn't say it was
really questions and answers it was more
of a forum for programmers which was
mostly full of questions and answers and
experts exchange had a nice run of being
free and open to the public but then
failed as a business and when they
failed as a business I believe that the
story is that somebody else bought it
and immediately put up a pay wall and
started charging a monthly fee to get
into experts
and saying well this is how we're gonna
succeeded as a business and that was
sort of infuriating to people because
they had contributed all of their
knowledge to this site as a volunteer
effort sort of out of generosity and out
of a desire to help other people on the
Internet and now suddenly there was kind
of a private enterprise trying to make
money off of that and it was there was
also this sort of deceptive thing that
they did with Google where they gave
Google the answer Google Google does not
actually show results that go to a page
you have to pay for that's always been
an important principle of Google and so
they did this sort of deceptive thing
where they showed good Google the
results but they didn't really show you
the results and we can go on about that
for days and days the main point is that
the previous dominant player for a place
where people might get answers to their
problems was charging a lot of money and
it was sort of unfair because the
answers were coming from the community
who were writing the answers on a
volunteer basis and so when we started
Stack Overflow it was pretty easy just
to say hey we're just gonna be like that
only not evil and when we looked around
actually we saw that since the time of
forums a lot of neat stuff had been
invented on the internet about ways that
you can make communities work better and
function better and so we kind of
adopted as many of those ideas as we
could into Stack Overflow so just things
like voting on answers and then making
the best answer rise to the top and then
giving people a reputation that's based
on how many votes their answer is
received that's all stuff which is now
relatively commonplace but made Stack
Overflow much cleaner and nicer so
instead of finding a conversation when
you come in from a Google search what
you find is just the answer right there
at the top and that was a little bit
non-obvious people thought well it's a
forum you're not gonna be able to
understand the conversation if you don't
read it in chronological order and lo
and behold it turns out that that's not
the right order for a Q&A forum the
right order is you know let people vote
on how good the answers are and so there
was a bunch of stuff like that that we
kind of incorporated early on and we
made it a big hit but honestly you know
we got an awful lot of help out there
from the big incumbent player just being
a for pay site and then we figured out
how to do it for free prior to
starting stackoverflow at fog creek you
had almost the opposite approach where
you said free is over we're going to
make things that people pay for yeah
it's kind of funny that was a very
popular thing in the year 2000 because
there was this whole crash of the.com
and Evan Williams who created Twitter
and later OTO and and finally medium oh
and before Twitter it was a blogger
anyway that's a dwelt Williams and he
had written a blog post called the N at
free which was surprisingly influential
and it's now gone I don't think you can
find it even even know if it the
Internet Archive has it but he wrote
this very very influential piece around
then saying like look there was this
weird thing that happened because the
internet started out as a research
project and so everything on it was sort
of free by accident and in fact later it
was a government research project and so
there was some kind of stipulation that
you agreed not to use it for commercial
purposes and so there was this weird
history of the internet that it started
out saying things shall be free and
oddly enough there was this belief that
everything on the internet had to be
free but there doesn't actually have to
be the case you know we were assuming
that but maybe that's not really true
and so when all of these companies that
had started out offering ridiculous
things for free on the internet
all failed there was kind of a backlash
and and that was what about blog post
was about at the end of free maybe we
can't actually do this anymore turns out
that it wasn't the end of free and that
was wrong but that was just the the
generation I guess that was the era so
even though it wasn't the end of free
there's still a contrast between two
different kinds kinds of companies that
get big fast kind versus organic growth
you talked about this at Y Combinator
startup school could you please explain
the difference between get big fast
companies and maybe how Stack Overflow
became a get big fast by accident yeah
there's an article there's an article on
my blog or a an old blog post called Ben
and Jerry's versus Amazon and it kind of
goes into all the different differences
because whether a company is oriented to
be a fast growth company or oriented to
be sort of a slow growth company did
Sherman's an awful lot of things and you
kind of got you got you kind of have to
decide and then you gotta line them all
up because you try to be one but then
you do the other then you kind of fail
like if you're in a business that needs
to be fast growth but you're trying to
do it as slow growth and somebody else
will will take over and I've made that
mistake myself at times and I've seen
that mistake made a lot the key decision
point is really I think probably
understanding whether this is a brand
new thing that's going to be a dominant
thing that everybody does I like to call
those land grab situations if there's a
new thing such as QA using gamification
or bug tracking or distributed version
control systems whatever that new thing
is and literally nobody is doing it and
at some point in the future literally
everybody will be doing it then the best
strategy is probably to be a fast growth
company in that situation whatever that
means and to grow as fast as possible to
try to capture as much territory as you
can so to speak so that you end up being
the dominant player because the slope in
that particular situation the slow
growth person will lose out to the fast
growth person but the other kind of
company is where you say you know what I
want to start a I don't know a music
festival and there's already a million
music festivals so now you have to
compete against all the incumbent music
festivals and you have to somehow do it
better but if the way that you're gonna
do it better is by growing faster that's
kind of wishful thinking and if the way
you're gonna do it better is by spending
more money then you have the fire
festival which was a well-known disaster
that was not even successful even if
they had spent the money and you still
don't have kind of an audience so in
that particular business you got to
quietly pry away customers from other
businesses so to speak that's not a land
grab that's more of a build a business
in an established category and an
established category you really have to
build for the long term and you have to
build from a position of bootstrapping
with profitability and you can invest a
little bit but you have to be really
careful about what you're doing and so
those are the two kinds of businesses I
think fog Creek was started basically
with the idea of being slow growth
versus stock overflow it became evident
really quickly that it was growing fast
incredibly fast yeah
right then there could be situations in
the middle and maybe you could talk
about Trello is that a situation in the
middle because it seems like there are
sort of Kanban board type software out
there there could potentially be
incumbents but then you ended up making
it into product that did achieve a lot
of scale and how did you manage to
identify the right strategy for that
I think Trello is actually in a kind of
a greenfield market believe it or not I
do think it had to be fast growth and we
thought that even at the beginning
although it looks like a Kanban board at
first it's nothing about how it
functions in the marketplaces is Kanban
board like and very few of the Trello
boards that are out there in the wild
are being used in the same way as a
Kanban board with cards progressing from
left to right and actually that was one
of the key insights didn't that caused
it to be any much larger category than
the Kanban category which confused the
heck out all the people that were doing
Kanban boards and they look at Trello
and they're like why is this such a big
deal we've had this since you know 1903
or whoops and whatever whenever they had
it so it was always meant to be kind of
a high-growth business we always
intended that we always knew it and the
only thing that was middle about it is
that for a while for the first trying to
remember I think 11 employees of Trello
we were able to just fund that
completely out of fog creeks profits and
that gave us the opportunity to delay
raising venture capital for Trello until
it was already a huge success and
raising venture capital when you're
already a huge success is easy and you
give up less equity and so that was kind
of everything went right in in the story
of Trello kind of we got to raise VC a
little bit later and actually that
particular story is repeating itself
with glitch right now I'm not the right
person to go into the details but glitch
is sort of another example of something
that was funded internally at fog Creek
for quite a while from the profits of
the other businesses and was able to
grow and achieve you know very very
rapid growth internally which made it
easier hypothetically makes it easier to
raise venture capital should they choose
to do so
and so that's those are what I would
call kind of a fast growth business and
then it's just that we were kind of
lucky enough to get to
the series a without really having a
seed round you know or an angel round so
to speak and thus making the terms in
the first fundraising round better could
you go into detail a little bit more
about that for our listeners that maybe
don't have experience with venture
capital or startups maybe it seems like
common sense but as a developer I don't
understand the way that venture capital
is think yeah so could you run through
that example a little bit explain how
did it make fundraising easier okay
let's start with what does a venture
capitalist doing they are they're
investing money in companies that have
the potential to grow a huge amount but
also might be complete failures and so
they're what their profile looks like if
they're successful is maybe I invested
in 20 companies and two of them were
unbelievably huge successes that
returned all the money that I put in and
then some and then maybe three more kind
of returns a decent amount of money and
all the other ones failed so that's what
the world looks like from a venture
capitalist perspective and so when
you're looking for money you're not so
much looking for a sure thing you're
looking for something that if it is
successful is going to return a
thousandfold or you know even you know
whatever it's gonna return 10x your
money that's considered a huge success
it's like I put in I put in a million
dollars and I got 10 million MIT dollars
back a few years later so that's their
perspective that's what they're looking
for and if that's not what you want as a
company then then that particular type
of investment is not the right
investment for you so the second
question is if there's a bunch of people
out there that want to invest in you
what's the strategy assuming your
business is going to be useful what's
the strategy to keep as much ownership
of your company as possible rather than
just kind of giving it all away to
investors so you give it all away to
investors first of all it's not good for
you because you don't own it and then
you don't get rich but also it's not so
great for the investors because you're
you don't have as much of a financial
incentive to make the company successful
if you don't own a big chunk of it so
you want to you know as a founder of a
company or to kind of maybe even I would
say the first few employees of a company
theoretically you want to give away as
few shares as possible in your company
to investors to to be seize all else
being equal so another question is when
an investor invests in you
much money will they give you in
exchange for what percentage of your
company so we could call that kind of
the multiple or something and ideally
what you want to get is you want them to
give you the maximum amount of money for
the smallest possible percentage of your
company right like I would much rather
somebody gave me ten million dollars for
ten percent then ten million dollars for
five percent no I would rather ten
minutes for five percent right so what
does that mean that means that we would
rather have the implied valuation of the
company of that investment should be as
high as possible I want investors to
consider my company to be as valuable as
possible so they're willing to pay a lot
for a small number of shares so what
would cause investors to think my
company is very valuable well there are
two things one is it's making a lot of
money and other is it's growing really
fast but actually there's sort of a
third thing which dominates both of
those which is how risky is it really
how much chance is there that the whole
thing blows up or that there really is
no market or that the drug that you said
that you're discovering turns out not to
work or whatever it is that you're
trying to build is is turns out to be a
failure how much how much risk is
involved and so the less risk there is
the more valuable your company is and
that should be kind of obvious right
because you're investing in a bunch of
companies they're all pretty risky but
you want the the least risky run should
be worth more all right now what is how
do you even define risk how risky is a
given started when you look at a
start-up the way you define risk is by
looking at the proof points what has the
company already proven so there's a
whole bunch of things that a company has
to prove think of a start-up starting
tomorrow you go out and start a new
company you got to prove a whole bunch
of things before your company's worth a
billion dollars number one you better
prove that you've got your you're even
going to start the company number two
you got to prove that you can recruit
some co-founders number three you got to
prove that you can get your first
customer dollar number four you got to
prove that you can build the product you
want to build if you need engineers to
write code you got to prove that they
can code it then you got to prove that
the market wants that code then you got
to prove that if the market is using
your program that they will tell their
friends about it and therefore it will
grow naturally through word-of-mouth and
then you got to prove what that growth
rate is and then you got to prove that
this thing provides some value and then
you got to prove the people will pay for
the value and then you got to prove that
the amount of money they pay is more
than the amount of money it costs you to
provide the service and therefore you
can
in a profitable way so I could just list
these all day long and there's all these
different things you have to prove and a
good venture capitalist will come in and
say okay the more of these things that
you prove the more valuable your company
is it's not that I need you to prove
them all in advance like you have to
give me a document proving everything
formally before you get your first cent
it's like I understand that you haven't
proven any of these things but the less
of the things that you've proven the
less valuable your company is so if all
you've proven is that you haven't a good
idea your company might only be worth a
small amount of money and so I will give
you a small amount of money but you
better be giving me a big percentage of
your company in exchange for that small
amount of money right so in that
particular world the way to think about
it is the more things you can prove
about your company the more valuable it
will be and so you want to prove as many
things as possible about your company
early before you take that big
investment and if you're going to take
multiple investments which you probably
should you want to stage them so that
each investment comes after you've just
proven something very important like we
just got to profitability or we just got
to the point where somebody is using our
product and paying us for it all of
those proof points are we just got to
the point where we've hired an
engineering team whatever those points
are they make your company more valuable
and so every time you make the company
more valuable you can raise a little bit
more money at a better valuation and if
you follow that strategy you'll end up
controlling the largest potential
percentage of your company so in the
earlier story that I told about Trello
luckily we had enough money to prove
everything in-house we were able to
prove that we could build a product that
we could recruit the people that it was
usable that people liked it that when
they used it they shared it with their
friends that we could get people I can't
remember if we got people paying for it
before we took the venture capital but
having proven a lot of those things in
having a big base of millions of users
already then when you went out to VCS
they had to pay up in other words they
had to pay high valuations because they
knew that this was a reasonably
successful company that proven a lot of
things and other companies had not
proven and what that meant was that the
percentage of the company that we had to
give to investors which is much lower
and that meant that when we did sell
Trello to Atlassian we got to keep a
higher percentage of the dollars that
they gave us you explained that venture
capitalists well gladly
let a lot of their companies fail as
long as a few key ones succeed it sort
of sounds like you might be the turtle
that doesn't make it to the water yeah
and in that situation what you have to
consider do you have to think about your
tolerance for risk what do you have to
think about do you want this company to
succeed no matter what for some personal
reason how do you juggle that decision
those are all true things yeah you have
to think about your personal talents for
risk you also have to think about what's
really you know what has actually gone
wrong and what's the actual situation
you're in actually even though people
talk about companies just failing and
then companies being super successes in
the average VC portfolio there's a big
middle of companies that you might think
of as sometimes called the walking dead
which is a horrible term but companies
that are just not gonna grow any further
than they've already grown they're not
losing money maybe they're making a
small amount of money and they're
accomplishing some good for the world
and the people like the products it's
just never gonna be big maybe the
leadership doesn't have a vision for
getting any bigger than this maybe the
market wouldn't support this particular
idea any further than it's already gone
but for whatever reason I think the VCS
look at those companies and say we've
given up we're probably not gonna make
that much money on these companies it's
best to at least save time and not waste
any time with them because you know
that's kind of the worst thing to a VC
is if you've invested a day every week
helping out some company it's not going
to go anywhere so but to the person in
that company they may have accomplished
their mission they might have had a
mission to you know make the world's
better for Turtles getting out to sea
through you know they dove turtle
application software and they made it
and there's not a big market for that
but they're profitable and they're you
know they're they're still going and and
and they're meeting their mission which
was their goal and that's fine there's
another thing when you think about risk
actually is you do kind of have to ask
yourself is it so bad to fail what's the
what's what's the real cost and that has
to do with your personal taste as a
founder the truth is that in the United
States in the high-tech entrepreneurial
economy nobody's gonna go hungry
honestly if you've done a start-up if
you built a thing if you were able to
raise some seed capital early on and get
a couple of early
customers you've probably had enough
money to live off of once you raise
money you're taking home a salary so
it's not you know no worse scenario than
having another job maybe it's a slightly
lower salary maybe there's some
opportunity cost for having done
something better but it's not like the
the punishment is that you're your get
your head chopped off by it by a
guillotine or you're sent to prison you
know the punishment is your worst case
scenario you gonna have to work you
gotta go get a job at JPMorgan that puts
things in perspective you said in one of
your talks that people think of you as a
risk taker but you see yourself as more
of a scaredy-cat is that is that true
like how did how did a scaredy-cat
become founder of multiple successful
companies yeah as I get older I kind of
learned more about that you know sort of
the distinction between those two
categories one thing I've noticed about
myself is I'm definitely not an early
adopter I don't have any of those
devices in your home that you you talk
to them and then they tell you what the
weather is out of sort of paranoia I
tend to be the last person to install
the new social network so I was able to
completely skip snapchat which is nice
and that came and went and and kind of
hoping to be able to skip tick tock but
I'm just I'm always late to these little
parties I don't know why I'm not
interested in like the newest and the
latest things and I do tend to be very
very careful and all the businesses that
I've started it's usually been because
it's just an overwhelming sense that
there's an overwhelmingly obvious
opportunity here and I know all the
steps and I can see how this would be
done and it all kind of makes sense and
I just have a a real feeling of like
there really is no risk here this is an
this is a clearly obvious thing that's
the late adopters advantage yeah it can
be and it doesn't necessarily mean
you're copying somebody but it does sort
of speak to sort of the obvious nosov
the opportunity I think Stack Overflow
is one of those things it was really
weird to me that nobody started I mean
there was a the whole time that this
experts exchange shenanigans on Google
was going on it was probably five years
where every developer was like oh I hate
it when you do any kind of search and
experts exchange comes up and then you
click on and then it asks you to pay and
you can't and then the
that was just like how hard is it to
make why did nobody just take forum
software generic cheap online web form
software and slap it up somewhere and
say hey go here instead of experts you
change you guys and and that'll be the
new alternative and I kept thinking
somebody's gonna do that and shock me
that nobody did and after like a year of
nobody doing that when I first had the
idea for Stack Overflow I that was like
hey we just got to do this if he had
seen somebody else doing it what do you
have do you think he would have gone
forward oh I would have helped them you
know it's like somebody already added
I'd be like yay good everybody go here
another thing I want to say is that some
of the most successful businesses I
won't say 100% but I would go with like
94% of the most successful entrepreneurs
and founders are founders who are huge
believers in the thing that they're
building they would do it anyway even if
they're doing it cuz of a mission
they're like the world has to be
different I'm doing this thing because
the world is broken I'm gonna make the
world better the founders that are not
so successful the one who like who I
want to start a company that sounds cool
I went and saw this movie called the
social network with Mark Zuckerberg and
he made Facebook and he got rich and it
seemed really fun and I want to do that
because that seems fun what thing can I
do that's fun and then they sort of cast
around for a business idea and they go
out go for that and that doesn't that
doesn't lead to anything
the successful founders are super
mission driven they see a huge
opportunity they need the world to be
reconfigured in this particular way and
then they dive into to reconfigure it
and that's kind of what keeps them going
through the hard times and the good is
that mission driven part because
everybody else starts and then they just
give up what I'm gonna go and get stuff
and that I think is often the hallmark
of a good entrepreneur is you sort of
ask them well if the thing what would
you what would you do if you discovered
that the thing you're trying to invent
here already exists and somebody's
already making it and I think the good
founder would say huh oh good alright
now I don't have to work on that I can
work on something better or different
and then they just sort of step back if
somebody was really doing it well you
know if somebody's doing it badly they
would look at it and say oh yeah but
here's the problem they don't understand
that ABC and I understand ABC and
therefore my thing is gonna be
successful whereas that thing is not
going to be successful but and we need
this to both
exist and be successful so it's not
enough that somebody else is doing it
it's got to work your code is powerful
and so are you and when you consider the
reach of your code it's clear that to
deliver quality code you must also
deliver secure code marking you start a
first step is educating yourself on
basic secure coding principles and
beginning to put these principles into
practice every day very codes secure
coding toolkit is your go-to resource
for all your secure coding needs the
benefits of our toolkit include learning
best practices for secure coding
understanding how to secure your DevOps
environments learning to combat the most
common software vulnerabilities stay
secure and download this valuable asset
today
ww-where code comm / SC radio even when
you started your first company fog Creek
you had a vision you didn't see any good
companies to work for in New York City
you saw that developers couldn't find a
company they want to work for companies
said they couldn't find developers so
you wanted to create a company that
developers wanted to work for yeah and I
think it's really interesting it almost
seems like you ran a like a pirate ship
everyone was splitting the revenue is
that true yeah there was a lot of that
early on we had profit sharing and we
sort of just lit up the profit yeah you
know cut kind of to that point of the
mission of the original Falkirk it was
say there's a little bit more it's a
simpler mission than the mission of
stacker fo it was just like just no good
places for programmers in New York which
is strange there's definitely good
places in Silicon Valley and there's
good places like Microsoft is a great
place to work in Seattle excuse me
Redmond and one thing that happened is
like three or four years after I started
fog Creek Google opened up a big office
in New York and said you know what
there's gonna be a big office in New
York I'm gonna be a programmers they're
gonna be developers writing code in New
York and Google really got what it takes
to make a place for developers and want
to work and they were working on a kind
of amazing mission really cool stuff
lots of big computers you could play
with and I thought AHA cat if they had
just started four years earlier they
could have saved me August trouble
because I would have just gone and
worked there I would have had the start
fog Greek and you know it really was
that that's that's how you know the
mission is if is if somebody else had
done it
you wouldn't bother that's how you know
that the mission is is kind of the the
thing that's gonna be the calling do you
think that that's caught on by and large
at the companies out there are they
making companies that you would want to
work for today a bunch of it has it has
gotten in general it has gotten to be
much better today to be a programmer
than it used to be there's one area
where maybe I'm just in massive
disagreement with the whole world but I
still think that there's way too many
companies out there even the 90% or more
of companies think that the right way to
make a work environment for programmers
is just to put them all in big long
desks shoulder-to-shoulder and in kind
of a big one room environment and in
fact Facebook is now built you know a
8-acre room for all their people to work
in and that seems to be kind of par for
the course is working together and just
having to overhear everything that goes
on and I'm still a big big big big
believer in private offices and quiet
workspaces especially pretty good kind
of concentrating to you as a programmer
I don't want to overhear conversations
as a programmer at all ever I want to be
able to concentrate and get work done
and when I'm done I'm happy to go into
the slack channel and see what people
have been talking about and I'll catch
up then but please don't interrupt me
with something
least of all something interesting
that's gonna drag me away because when
you leave coding for even a minute you
go back to it you've forgotten
everything so I'm this huge believer in
quiet private workspaces whatever that
means it doesn't necessarily have to be
a private office but it's Stack Overflow
we have everybody either has a private
office or works from their own home
where by the way even though we love
remote workers they are required to have
a quiet private place at home they can't
just be you know the dining room table
unless that's quiet and private in your
home but that is I think a requirement
on the other hand there's a lot of stuff
that you see now it's very very
commonplace across Silicon Valley you
might be free lunches free soda dry
cleaning services on-site all the kind
of stuff that really meant - first of
all signals of developers that they're
important but also just give them kind
of a plush environment to work from
which shows respect for the value of the
work that they're doing which i think is
extremely valuable
and I started fog great because nobody
value programmers in New York City they
really thought of programmers as being
some kind of awkward typist that's just
annoying I want to talk more a little
bit later about how our listeners can
make sure that they find out the right
company that provides the right
environment so they can be happy they
can feel productive but well I have you
in the ranting mood a lot of what I like
to read about your blog and people I
knew in my previous company enjoyed
sharing your articles and it's because
of those rants about how to make your
workplace good and we would I think that
there's a certain catharsis doesn't
develop you're like I know there's
something wrong at least you know I feel
like somebody understands yeah it's
interesting that now Stack Overflow is
almost like a remote first company
whereas before you were talking about
how people should be in an office it
should be a nice environment you you
haven't changed that you're still
consistent with that point of view but
now you're bringing in this remote
concept and I would love to hear you
rant about how to do a remote work right
and how are people doing a remote wrong
yeah the quick answer is that when
you're on a remote team it has to be
remote first so taking one person and
making them a telecommuter it's not
going to work because the rest of the
team will ignore that person and that
person will rapidly get out of the loop
and that will cause problems so if
you're gonna have a remote team it has
to either be everybody's remote or in
some cases like it Stack Overflow there
are people who come into the office but
they always work through the internet
with each other they don't go into a
meeting and have a meeting in a room the
meetings are online the technology has
gotten better which is why I changed my
mind now we have video conferencing
that's for all intents and purposes free
that's excellent where you can have as
many people as you want in a video
conference we have slack which is cheap
and we have even free versions of that
that are available so it's easy and
cheap now to do a good job of allowing
people to communicate through typing
through chat rooms through the tools
that they use like if you're using
github and just reading each other's
check-ins and commits through video
conferencing and even just audio
conferencing on the I prefer video if
it's gonna be some of you work with
regularly and the tools have gotten so
good that there's no reason to
physically come into the office anymore
as long as everybody's using them if you
have this weird situation where there
are five people and they decide to have
a meeting they go into a conference room
and now there's one person who lives in
Portland so he's not here and so they
got to fiddle around a little bit with
the video conferencing system and now
that person is on a TV screen but
everybody else is in person that's not a
real meeting that that person is already
in in a good position so that's that's
the way that you have to do it another
important thing that we learned is that
everybody has to be approximately on the
same time zone so the guideline I've
used since the beginning of time is for
an engineering team pick your time zone
and then make sure that everybody is
there during the afternoon of that time
zone for us it's the New York afternoons
and that means if you're on the East
Coast you've got to work New York
afternoons and you can stay later or you
can come in earlier if you're on the
west coast you got to get to work by
9:00 a.m. because that becomes New York
afternoon if you're in Europe you're
gonna have to stay a little bit late and
work during other people's dinner time
but that may not be a problem for you if
you're in Asia you can't do it and
that's that's what it means to pick a
timezone and what that means is that
team is always there and so you can have
conversations with people as a drop drop
of a notice just the real problem
happens if you start to split people up
between let's say India and San
Francisco now they are I'm not sure what
the number is I think ten ten and a half
hours apart or something like that ten
hours apart that's enough so that
they're never working at the same time
and that means that every conversation
has an incredibly high latency thing
built into the conversation like right
in the middle of every sentence so you
can't have a rapid back-and-forth and
gain understanding with somebody and
when you start doing that you're like oh
wow I got to tell the Union dev team
that they need to do a B and C and you
fire off an email and you send it to
them and you don't expect them to see it
until they get to work in six hours and
then they get to work and they see it
and they don't understand or they
misunderstand but you don't even know
that and so maybe they fire back a list
of questions and then you fire back a
list of answers and now a week has
elapsed do the math and and now and you
don't realize that you're gonna be in
this state for another four weeks before
you say you know what this is taking too
long can we just get on the call
together and now somebody's got to wake
up at 2:00 a.m. so that is another
example of something that does not work
with the remote teams
so never do that but we've had a lot of
success where people are working at the
same time for most of the day and
there's always time on any given day to
have a rapid back and forth and make
decisions have you been able to scale
out to other time zones like pick some
part of the product or pick some
separate product and put them in a
separate time zone or does that not work
for you you know you always want to but
it's very hard to add I'm sure that if
at scale you can figure out ways to do
it if you're a company like Amazon that
has a lot of micro services or a company
let me think of an example if you have
done a really good job of splitting up
your services in such a way that the
interfaces between them are almost
commercial right like so for example if
somebody needs storage somebody if a
programmer working in Amazon needs
storage they're gonna use Amazon storage
and they're using a commercial Amazon
product it is available commercially and
so because that boundary because amazon
has created the boundary between how
they do storage and the entire world
meaning they have a product support site
and there's escalation and there's tech
support and you can figure out how much
everything costs and you can pay for it
because that exists is a service that's
available to everybody it's certainly
available to internal Amazon programmers
and that kind of the formality of the
definition of the barrier between those
two things is so strong that you can
make it work and if you had that I
believe you could make it work in
reality I just think of one time where I
had a remote team that was not on my
time zone and I thought I got to just
define a contract with that team of
exactly what I need them to deliver and
I wrote the most detailed spec you've
ever seen in your life you would read it
and you would be astonished at how
little it left to the imagination and I
created C++ header files and said your
whole job is just to implement these
header files the header file to find the
detailed interface that I wanted with
this team and all they had to do is
write the code that met my interface
requirements and in fact they did almost
to deliver that however I did not make a
definition of how high-quality it has to
be and there was stuff that I left out
of the interface because there was stuff
that I forgot or I didn't know or I
couldn't figure out until it was built
and once it was built I looked at it and
I said this is really interesting if you
guys had been in the room next to me you
to come in here and said excuse me this
thing that you wrote doesn't make sense
but because you couldn't reach me you
tried to implement a thing that didn't
make sense and then you just sort of
left it at that and delivered that is
your deliverable so the real question is
can you make it work if you're not in
the same time zone as the other people
or maybe if you don't even speak the
same language as the other people and
that requires such a formal separation
of affairs that is so well defined and
so formalized that it's almost
impossible to make that to pull that off
in any normal organization sounds almost
like it needs to be separate companies
at that point yeah or em it could be the
same company as long as whatever the
border line is between the companies is
something that you would sell in by you
know that is sold in bought on the
market you know that sort of generically
available right like so I've got I don't
know I I can make up an example but you
know if this is the thing I can buy from
anybody I can certainly buy it for
myself but if it needs more definition
than that it's got to be more custom
than that then the level of conversation
we're gonna have to have in order to
figure that thing out engineer and
design it correctly figure that that
integration point is gonna require a lot
of rapid back-and-forth and if we can't
do that rapidly then we're gonna do that
slowly and if we do it slowly we're
gonna lose is there anything that people
are under investing in whether the
companies like remote company is not
investing a certain technology your
thing back in the day was company should
spend money on comfortable chairs and
big monitors and an office with the door
that closes yeah but but what's the
equivalent now that people aren't under
investing in wow man
yeah two big monitors Wow I'm not
amazing that developers don't have all
the monitors they want they don't have
to see our T's anymore III it has gotten
a lot better it's gotten better
certainly in the world that we know of
mainstream sort of Silicon Valley the
the norm has gotten really really good
there for getting developers the things
that they need I think it's still a
common thing that I still see
occasionally is the sort of false
economies and sometimes it's not even
the company that's making those
decisions a lot of times that comes from
the developers where you know we'll go
into a company we had this problem with
fog bugs and we have this problem a
stack overflow enterprise
go into big company and we'll say hey we
have seco flow it works great 30
companies have installed it and they're
all having fantastic success with
developers in-house asking questions
getting answers and it works amazing and
they use it even more than they use the
main Stack Overflow if you can believe
that they use their internal one a lot
more and so it's a huge success and
these other companies say yeah I don't
doubt it and we say would you like to
buy it and they say well we kind of have
a thing and you're like what do you have
and like well we sort of built something
in-house using some kind of macros I'm
not sure like how are you not sure what
you have there like I don't know I don't
use it like does anybody really use it
and then you sort of if you dig into it
you discover that there's a team of six
people maintaining an internal thing at
great cost that nobody uses because they
don't know what it is or what it's
called because it's not called Stack
Overflow
but it's costing them a fortune to have
their own little proprietary little I
made it here how hard could it be to
make a Stack Overflow clone and it turns
out it is hard and the amount they're
spending on their little proprietary
in-house one that's not working is way
more than it would cost them just to buy
it from us and get one that has ten
years of work put into it and you know
every corner has been polished to within
an inch of its life because we've been
working on this for ten years and making
it great for every possible situation
like why use that one that you have
in-house at much greater cost so there
is sort of a common thing where I think
developers just always feel like they
can roll their own wheel and they're
always inventing their own stuff instead
of instead of just going to buying
something that already exists it's
readily available on the market because
they kind of underestimate the value of
their own time they underestimate how
hard it's gonna be
and they underestimate the gap between
how much work it takes to make an
acceptable QA website and make a great
qnet website and you know the gap there
is like 99% like it's 1% of the work
will get you functioning QA and in a web
form of something that you can
distribute to your co-workers and
they'll be like oh yeah I see how this
kind of works like Stack Overflow but
then you need to do 100x as much work to
really get all the corner cases and the
bells and the whistles and make it
really really successful ok yeah that
points well-taken it's a good
illustration of false economies as you
mentioned I probably have to insert some
kind of disclosed
sure that at one point stackoverflow was
running an ad for Stack Overflow teams
on this podcasts oh okay cool
hey everybody use sticker flow teams
yeah so this is not an ad we're not
being paid to be on the show or
something like that
thank um but no we we have you here for
your point of view and but yeah that the
points well-taken so we're starting to
get to the end of time we have about
five minutes left and there are a few
things that I promise to talk about we
could revisit but I want to make sure
that we cover anything that you want to
talk about that we haven't covered yet
so the the things that that I promise to
talk about were developers using Stack
Overflow how to use it effectively and
the other thing was how to make sure
that your find the right company and the
right team to work on okay did you want
to cover one of those or did you want to
cover something else so I'll do I'll do
three things that will cover all these
topics one is how to ask questions
effectively and how do you stack
overflow effectively I think most of the
time the question you're looking for is
already on there and so getting good at
search will really help you a lot but
there's a great article by John ski
about how to ask questions on Stack
Overflow it's called writing the perfect
question so if you just google you could
Google writing the perfect question or
Google John skeet how to ask that's a
great article that's a great source for
people that are about to write their
first question online or have been doing
it not getting very good responses two
important points that I want to make
there's number one make sure that you've
explained the question in a way like try
explaining it to a rubber duck on your
on your desk or a stuffed bear or even
your coworker and make sure that you
have correctly even formulated the
questions you want to ask in a way that
at least one other person can answer
because a lot of times people write
questions and it's not even clear what
they're asking or they haven't really
included all the information that
somebody would need to help them with
their problem and and the other part is
see if you can get down to the minimum
amount of code that demonstrates the
problem that you're facing so the
perfect question on Stack Overflow is
going to be I did this and then maybe
one or two lines of code and I expected
this and a description of what they
thought that would do but what I got was
this other thing and then
explanation what they actually got and
that's almost the perfect question and
it's always gonna get you an answer if
you can put include those those three
parts what you did the minimum possible
use case of what you actually did what
you thought that was going to do because
if you just told us what you've got
and we all think that that's correct
because that's right then we're not
helping you and and what you expected to
get and and then we can kind of help you
so that's the the how to ask a question
part the second thing you asked was how
to know if you've got the right job it's
worth still looking up the Joel test I
hope that is still number one in Google
for Joel test the Joel test twelve steps
to better code it's basically twelve
quick questions that you can easily get
answers to as a part of your normal
interviewing process while whilst
interviewing for a company and they're a
little bit out of date but if you should
be able to figure them out so for
example item number six do you have an
up to date schedule let's say that
you're going in and interviewing at a
company and they're working on a big
version of some new particular project
then you can just ask them can you tell
me what the schedule is when you expect
this to ship and where you update what
percentage is complete and if they sort
of say yes here's the schedule we have
27 items and we have knocked off twelve
of them
that's an organized company that's gonna
be pleasant to work their stuff is gonna
you know the trains run on time at that
company if you go to a company you say
when's its gonna work you know like
it'll be finished when it's finished
it's like you know it keeps slipping we
don't know but we keep adding things and
then bla bla bla you're gonna discover
that that's a company where the trains
do not run on time you're not going to
enjoy working with that company so there
are twelve things like that on the
module test which you can use and you
can ask as you go through the process of
interviewing for a company before you
start there that was your second thing
and then you were nice enough to say is
there anything else you want to talk
about and there is there's something I
want to talk about which is what it
means to be friendly on Stack Overflow
so I believe many of your listeners or
Stack Overflow users and many of them
thankfully are writing answers to
questions and trying to help people both
newbies and experts on Stack Overflow
and that's very much appreciated and
that's sort of a wonderful thing about
Stack Overflow is it really is this
massive volunteer effort that is
absolutely fantastic to see of people
helping each other
and I only want to say one thing about
that and it's it's a thing that we're
really really focused on stackoverflow
which is how to be more welcoming to
newcomers in the field of programming
and that doesn't mean doing their
homework for them and that doesn't mean
when somebody comes in with a really
stupid question they've done no work and
no research and they kind of expect you
to do all that work for them that you
even have to give them the time of day
however do remember that it is very hard
to speak up in a room when you're a
newcomer especially if you don't look
like the other people in the room so if
you're a person of color if you're a
woman or some other minority you are in
a minority of programmers and when you
go into a room full of people that don't
look like you it's a little bit harder
to feel welcomed and so if that room of
people kind of ignores you you won't
feel welcome if they're rude to you
that's awful you're a newcomer they
should be polite to you but even if
they're merely polite to you that can
feel a little bit unwelcoming they
really as a as a newcomer people kind of
have to make an effort to reach out and
actually be actively friendly not just
neutral and that's something that I want
to see a lot more of on stackoverflow is
that active friendliness if you look at
some of the status changes do a really
good job of that I mean there's a lot of
cases on Stack Overflow where you see
that but it's like hey I see this is
your first question it's a really
interesting one that you asked and
here's the answer and that's kind of one
way of answering that question you know
a woman told me that she has taped her
first question on Stack Overflow and the
answer that she got was oh that's easy
followed by the answer there's just
those three words oh that's easy
there's nothing antagonistic about that
there's nothing mean about saying that's
easy but what the woman thought who
would ask this question was no it isn't
it was not easy for me I struggled with
this for five hours before I finally
realized that I had no recourse and I
had to ask on Stack Overflow which was
very scary and very daunting cuz all
those very professional programmers we
don't look at me strange and they didn't
even say something mean they just said
that's easy and what that made me feel
she told me was I felt like an impostor
I felt like maybe I don't belong in the
field of programming because if I'm
having so much trouble with this easy
stuff then maybe I should go find a
different career and that was just wrong
that was just not factually correct
this stuff is all hard for everyone to
begin with and the person saying that's
easy was possibly trying to even be
friendly certainly not trying to be
unfriendly but then that result was to
kind of create this environment of
making people feel like they're in the
wrong place I don't even want to say
unwelcome you know that's not that's
going too far many people feel like like
Impostors and that is a big big problem
because we need a lot more developers
than we have in the world today and we
need for the developers in the world
today to be more representative of a
population at large so it's not just the
Stanford graduates at Facebook deciding
how the future of the world shall go we
need a much more diverse group of people
programming and creating the future of
the world as they write that code and we
got a we got a nurture those programmers
and create those new programmers and
developers on Stack Overflow and it's
funny but to do that doesn't mean just
being like right just the facts your
official answer it means going further
and kind of reaching out and being
welcoming to the newcomers and saying
you know I'm glad you asked that because
I don't see anybody else having asked
that question I can see why it's easy to
get confused with that thing but don't
worry you got this here's the answer
that's that's a completely different
approach from you know oh that's easy or
here is your answer so that's my little
speech and rant and I appreciate your
having giving me the platform to give
you this rant because this is something
that's very important to us at Stack
Overflow is making that thing that all
developers have to use making it
something that helps people get into the
field of programming and get good at it
especially the people with good
intentions not the people that need
homework help but the people with good
intentions and and encourages them and
brings them into the field so thanks for
coming on the show and getting the
message out there thanks for having me
Nate for software engineering radio this
has been Nate black thanks for listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us at team at SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of SU
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening